Preliminary Guide to the Jonathan Barnett Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jonathan Barnett papers
1963-2002
MS 1733
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
24
The papers consist of correspondence; subject files; meeting records; city planning and design reports; notebooks and calendars; and published writings which document Jonathan Barnett's career as architect, consultant, educator, and writer in the area of urban design and planning.
Barnett, Jonathan
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jonathan Barnett, 1998, 2002.
Biographical / Historical
Jonathan Barnett was born on January 6, 1937, in Boston, Massachusetts. He received a B.A. from Yale College in 1958, where he was a Scholar of the House in Architecture; an M.A. from Cambridge University in 1960; and a M. Arch. from Yale in 1963. Following graduation, he worked for the firm of Smith, Haines, Lundberg and Waehler and designed several university buildings. In 1964 he became associate editor of the Architectural Record magazine. In 1965 he was an advisor to the John Lindsay mayoral campaign and in 1967 helped start the Urban Design Group at the New York City Planning Department, which he directed from 1969 – 1971. As a consultant in urban design and development, Barnett advises cities throughout the United States; private investors; and government agencies, such as the National Park Service and the New York State Urban Development Corporation. He was professor of architecture and director of the Graduate Program in Urban Design at the City College of New York and then professor of Practice in City and Regional Planning and director of the Urban Design Program at the University of Pennsylvania. Barnett is the author of numerous articles and books on city planning and urban design.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence; subject files; meeting records; city planning and design reports; notebooks and calendars; and published writings which document Jonathan Barnett's career as architect, consultant, educator, and writer in the area of urban design and planning.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 5-8, containing daily calendars and notebooks, require permission of the donor for access.
Boxes 4 and 16 of Accession 2003-M-015, containing daily calendars and notebooks, require permission of the donor for access.
Architecture and society -- United States; City planning -- United States; Urban renewal -- United States; Barnett, Jonathan
- Inventory
  - Subject Files
    - Alaska, 1977, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Allegheny County, Pittsburgh
      - Background, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Airport, 1986-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Homestead, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Memoranda, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Minutes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Boise, Idaho, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - City University of New York
      - Civil service examinations
        - Urban designer, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Assistant urban designer, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Doctorate in urban affairs [proposed curriculum], 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dead plan drafts [including Harlem, Manhattan], 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Design Process Committee/Panel, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 13)
    - Educational Facilities Laboratories [railway station project], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Environment and behavior, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Garland STPM Press [urban design book series], 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Gateway National Recreational Area
      - General, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Clark/Chermayeff, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Decisions, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Environmental impact, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Floyd Bennett Field, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - General management plan
        - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Press coverage, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Testimony, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Transportation, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - H.E. Butt Grocery Company, Texas
      - Memoranda, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Parking, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Hong Kong, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Institute for Urban Design [creation of fellows program], 1991 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Lindsay, John V. [materials from the 1965 Lindsay mayoral campaign pertaining to urban design advice], 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 32 - 35)
    - Louisville, Kentucky, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Museum of Modern Art
      - "The New City: Architecture and Urban Renewal" [exhibition], 1967 January 23-March 13 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - National growth, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Penn Yards [development of railroad yards], 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Public Buildings Cooperative Act of 1975, United States Senate (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Salt Lake City, Utah, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - South Street Seaport Museum, New York
      - Contract, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 43 - 44)
      - Plan criticism, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Preliminary projections, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Presentation, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Speeches [Museum of Modern Art, AIA], 1967 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Twin Parks, Bronx, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Urban Design, First National Conference on, 1978 October 18-21 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Urban Design Group, New York City Planning Group
      - Meeting records
        - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - 1968 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 52 - 53)
        - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Printed material, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Reports, zoning studies, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Urban design [printed material], 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Published writings
    - The Elusive City: Five Centuries of Design Ambition and Miscalculation, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - An Introduction to Urban Design, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Urban Design, as Public Policy [two copies in English; one in Japanese], 1974, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - New York City planning and design reports, 1963-1975 (Box 4)
  - Day calendars, 1967-1986 (Box 5–8)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Daily calendars require permission of the donor for access.
  - Notebooks, 1970-1988 (Box 8)
    Notebooks require permission of the donor for access.
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-015
  - Lectures, 1985-2002 (Box 1–2)
  - Articles, 1987-2000 (Box 3)
  - Calendars, notebooks, 1987-1997 (Box 4)
    Daily calendars and notebooks require permission of the donor for access.
  - Pittsburgh files, 1977-1991 (Box 5)
  - Norfolk files, 1987-2002 (Box 6–7)
  - Arlington - Daniel Island, 1980s, 1990s (Box 8)
  - Cleveland State, Allegheny, Irvington, Kansas City, 1980s (Box 9)
  - Cleveland, Kansas City, 1981-2000 (Box 10)
  - NEA, NYC, miscellaneous, 1980s, 1990s (Box 11)
  - Myrtle Beach - Pittsburgh, 1990s (Box 12)
  - Pittsburgh, Regional Plan Association, 1980s, 1990s (Box 13)
  - Sioux City - Wildwood, 1990s (Box 14)
  - Correspondence A-Z [ non-project related], 1971-2001 (Box 15)
  - Notebooks, 1990s (Box 16)